<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Karthik Ganeshram</title><link>/categories/reflection/</link><description>Recent content from Karthik Ganeshram</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/reflection/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Choosing Your Discomfort</title><link>/blog/choosing-your-discomfort/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/choosing-your-discomfort/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about how life is full: full of good, full of clarity, full of momentum. Right now, I’m in a place I genuinely love. Things feel aligned. I feel grounded. And even here, even at a point where I can honestly say I’m happy, I notice the choices I make still carry discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s funny, happiness doesn’t eliminate friction. It just makes it clearer. I see it for what it is. And I realize the only real choice is which discomfort I’m willing to carry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can choose the discomfort of risk - of putting myself forward, stepping into something uncertain, letting outcomes happen that I can’t fully control. It hits fast. Sharp. Immediate. And it teaches. It shows me what works, what doesn’t. It adds texture to life. Even if things don’t go perfectly, I gain clarity. I feel alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or I can choose the discomfort of hesitation - holding back, wondering, replaying possibilities in my head. It feels safe, even comfortable at first. But it lingers. It doesn’t teach. It doesn’t move me. It just sits quietly, weighing more the longer I leave it alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find myself drawn to the discomfort that moves me. The one that’s honest and present. The kind that sharpens my sense of self, stretches my understanding, and keeps life vivid. Moving feels better but that doesn’t mean I want to be reckless. I want edges, but edges with awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in a place of happiness, I don’t want comfort to lull me into stasis. I want edges. I want clarity. I want growth. I want the kind of discomfort that makes life feel expansive rather than restrained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so I keep choosing it. Not because life is hard, not because I’m chasing challenge for its own sake, but because the friction of action, of engagement, of presence, adds to the life I already love. It amplifies it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happiness and growth aren’t opposites. They coexist. The discomfort I choose is part of that. It’s part of why life feels alive, why the present feels rich, why I can trust myself to navigate what comes next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that feels like the best kind of discomfort there is.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Note to Myself: Let Things Unfold</title><link>/blog/a-note-to-myself-let-things-unfold/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/a-note-to-myself-let-things-unfold/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Lately, I have been thinking about how some things take shape quietly, without announcement. It has been a calm month, and with all the walking I have been doing, reflection has started to feel less intentional and more natural. Small habits like a morning coffee, practicing latte art, or noticing light while taking photos have become gentle anchors in my day. They ground me while still leaving space to think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am noticing how certain moments feel unexpectedly close, even within the ordinary rhythm of life. There is a subtle richness in paying attention. To someone’s honesty. To shared presence. Or simply to the way things unfold in their own time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I am becoming more aware of the gaps that naturally exist between people. Differences in timing, perspective, or focus. I am learning to observe those gaps without trying to resolve them, without needing to force connection or define it. There is a quiet freedom in allowing things to be exactly as they are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also noticing how open I have become to new situations and experiences that arrive without a script. Saying yes, even without knowing what will come of it, feels like a gentle practice in trust. Trust in the present. Trust in myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some parts of life are still unfolding. Some connections are deepening, while others are loosening. And that feels okay. I am learning to hold curiosity and gratitude at the same time, allowing my own journey to exist alongside the natural currents of life, quietly and without judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, noticing, listening, and being present feels like enough.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Year in Review: 3.8 Million Steps, Forward</title><link>/blog/a-year-in-review-3.8-million-steps-forward/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/a-year-in-review-3.8-million-steps-forward/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve written reflections throughout the year about different parts of my life. Work, health, mindset, relationships. Looking back at them now, there’s a clear thread running through all of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had to name this year, I’d call it a year of consistency and growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of my life, I was good at starting things but struggled to see them through. That gap quietly bothered me, especially when it came to taking care of myself. This year, something changed. Not through motivation or intensity, but through showing up repeatedly and trusting the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consistency became a form of self-respect. A way of trusting myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="rebuilding-from-an-unsteady-start"&gt;Rebuilding from an unsteady start&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year didn’t begin on a high note. I started it feeling mentally off balance, unsure if I was doing enough and uncertain about direction. I carried a quiet pressure about where I should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What turned things around wasn’t a single breakthrough, but momentum built slowly. Small routines. Repeated effort. Less planning, more follow-through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fitness became the anchor!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regular gym training and the help of a personal trainer, consistency finally stuck. Having that structure, and someone pushing me beyond comfort zones I would have settled into on my own, made a real difference. Not just physically, but mentally as well. Viktoriia played a big role in that. Her coaching helped me trust discipline over motivation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lost weight, built muscle, and grew more comfortable in my body. The mental health benefits mattered just as much as the physical ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/review_2025/gym.png" alt="picture in the gym"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="falling-back-in-love-with-biking"&gt;Falling back in love with biking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I rediscovered how much I love biking. After deciding to take it seriously, I rode around 4,000 km, and it quickly became more than just exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biking gives me calm. It’s where my thoughts slow down and sort themselves out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some rides stand out. Being challenged into a 150 km ride when I had only asked for a 100 km route and finishing it. Long rides through Belgium, including a memorable one from Ghent to Knokke. Catching the beginning of the Tour de France in Lille. Chasing sunrises and sunsets again, simply for the joy of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biking also became social in the best way. Shared effort, long conversations, and quiet stretches where nothing needed to be said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big part of that was riding with Florian, who pushed me not just on the bike but in how I approached the year overall. What started with bikes gradually spilled into other parts of life. Having someone around who shares similar values and a desire to keep improving made this year feel less solitary and more grounded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only started riding consistently in June, and I spent large parts of September and October away from home. Knowing that makes this year feel even more encouraging. Next year, my goal is to ride 7,000 km. Not as a stretch for the sake of it, but as a continuation of something that has already become part of who I am. I would also love to take a biking vacation sometime next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/review_2025/cycling.png" alt="Bikng with friends"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="presence-not-just-progress"&gt;Presence, not just progress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhere along the way, I started living more in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still care about goals, but I’m no longer always chasing the next one at the expense of the present. I find joy now in simple things. Running in the rain. A really good pastry with coffee. Quiet mornings. Being outside whenever I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve intentionally spent less time on tech outside of work and more time grounded in the real world. That shift alone has made life feel lighter and more balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the most memorable moments this year were the smallest ones. Discovering a love for really good pastries and coffee. Sitting somewhere warm on a slow morning. Chasing sunrises and sunsets without a plan. These moments grounded me in the present and reminded me that joy doesn’t always come from milestones. Sometimes it’s already there if I’m paying attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/review_2025/small_things.png" alt="collage of pictures"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="work-balance-and-momentum"&gt;Work, balance, and momentum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professionally, this was a strong year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave two conference talks, something I had wanted to do for a long time. Not everything went perfectly, including broken demos, but that was never the point. It was a start, and it gave me confidence. I want to do more of this going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The startup I work for was acquired, and I was promoted to Senior Software Engineer. I’m genuinely enjoying my work and curious about what the next year holds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as importantly, I’ve improved my work-life balance. I’m more intentional about how I spend my time and better at stepping away when needed. Enjoying my work while still having space for life outside of it has made a meaningful difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reading-and-perspective"&gt;Reading and perspective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read around 20 books this year. The Book of Why and Clear Thinking stood out for how they shaped the way I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading, for me, is about expanding perspective. I started strong, slowed down later, and want to be more intentional about it again next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="relationships-boundaries-and-growing-up"&gt;Relationships, boundaries, and growing up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some relationships deepened this year, built on shared values, mutual effort, and a genuine desire to keep improving. Others faded, and I learned that it’s okay to let go when the effort becomes unidirectional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve become better at setting boundaries and kinder to myself because of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also changed how I socialize at home. I still enjoy spending time in larger groups, but when it comes to dinners, I started hosting smaller ones more often. I invite one or two people over and cook together. It’s easier on my social battery, simpler logistically, and more meaningful. In many ways, it feels like a quiet step into being a more grounded adult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I express gratitude more often now, and I feel more confident talking to people. Next year, I want to keep meeting new people, expanding my circle, and building meaningful connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="travel-independence-and-roots"&gt;Travel, independence, and roots&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took a short solo trip to Copenhagen on a whim and spent a few days on my own. It reminded me how much I enjoy solo travel, something I used to do more and want to return to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also traveled with close friends and coworkers, each trip meaningful in its own way. Each of those trips helped me builder a closer bond to the people that I travelled with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most special moments this year was visiting India to surprise my mom for her 50th birthday. I hadn’t been back in a couple of years, and the trip made me reflect on how living in three different countries has shaped me. There are cultural clashes I’m still figuring out, and I’m okay letting that unfold slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="closing-the-year-with-gratitude"&gt;Closing the year with gratitude&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next year, I want to continue, not restart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to stay consistent. With the gym. With running, with the goal of a half marathon on my birthday. With writing. With how I show up for people. I want to keep living in the moment, educate myself financially, build relationships, and explore new activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of all, I’m grateful. For my health, for consistency, and for the people in my life who showed up for me, supported me, challenged me, and shared parts of this year with me, even when they didn’t realize the impact they were having.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to my Garmin, I took 3.8 million steps this year. Not all of them were deliberate. Some were hesitant, some confident, some taken on days when motivation was low. Taken together, they moved me forward quietly and consistently, one step at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful for quiet mornings, long rides, meaningful conversations, and a year that reminded me I can trust myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been one of the best years of my life. Not because it was perfect, but because I kept stepping forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that feels like the right place to continue from!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Joy of the Pause</title><link>/blog/the-joy-of-the-pause/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/the-joy-of-the-pause/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I have learned something about myself over the years. Whenever I reach a goal, I celebrate, but I also tend to move on quickly. Historically, my celebrations were short lived bursts of joy. Bright, enthusiastic, and gone almost before I had time to look around and appreciate what I had actually done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My happiness has always been genuine. It often involves a pastry, which is probably the most reliable reward system I have ever invented. I sit there with something sweet and comforting, enjoy the moment fully, and feel proud of myself. But by the time I am brushing off the last crumbs, my mind is already getting restless. It starts looking for the next mountain, the next idea, the next challenge. Apparently I have an inner endurance athlete who believes recovery time should be optional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of that, my life has often felt a bit like completing a long, tough hike, finally reaching the summit, taking one victorious photo, and then immediately checking the map to see what other trails I can do before the sun sets. I do not skip the accomplishment, but I definitely do not linger either. I go from summit to summit at a pace that surprises even me sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I have tried something different. I am making a conscious effort to let success settle in. I stay with the feeling of achievement longer. I savor the pastry instead of inhaling it. I let myself sit at the summit before rushing down the trail to find a new challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the surprising part is how much lighter everything feels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With fewer self imposed deadlines swirling in my head, I have noticed a level of calm that used to feel out of reach. Without the constant pressure to chase the next big thing, I enjoy my days more. I feel more grounded and more present. It is as if my mind finally set down a heavy backpack it did not need to carry. The weight of the endless push forward has eased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving myself permission to pause has made a real difference in my mental health. I feel more balanced. I feel more able to appreciate small joys. I feel more connected to my own life instead of racing through it. The pauses have not slowed my ambition. They have simply made it more sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still love new goals. I still get excited about fresh possibilities. That part of me is alive and well. It is just no longer running the entire show. It has learned to wait while I enjoy the view at the top. It has learned that rest is not the enemy of progress. It is part of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am, taking longer celebrations, eating pastries at a normal pace, and allowing myself to stay in the moment. The next goal will be there when I am ready. For now, it feels good to breathe a little more and push a little less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, the pastries taste even better this way!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Coffee, Pastries, and the Joy in the Little Things</title><link>/blog/coffee-pastries-and-the-joy-in-the-little-things/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/coffee-pastries-and-the-joy-in-the-little-things/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve always had a sweet tooth. But this year, that small craving has grown into something much bigger, a lens through which I’ve been noticing joy in unexpected, everyday moments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all started back in March while traveling. In Porto with a friend, we turned bakery-hopping into a game: stopping at nearly every bakery we passed and tasting pastéis de nata and other treats. When I got home, I couldn’t stop thinking about them, so I decided to bake pastéis de nata from scratch. They weren’t perfect, but the process reminded me that small efforts like whisking custard or folding pastry can bring a lot of satisfaction, even if the result isn’t flawless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks later, I was in Barcelona with a coworker, continuing the tradition of wandering into bakeries. By the end of the trip, it was clear that I wasn’t just enjoying pastries, I was savoring the simple, grounding pleasure of experiencing them fully, and it always felt even better with a good cup of coffee in hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in Rotterdam, this curiosity for small joys found its rhythm. At first, pastries and coffee were simply a reward for finishing a morning run - a small, deliberate indulgence that made early mornings feel lighter. Soon I began sharing them with a friend, turning it into a weekly ritual: picking up pastries and meeting to catch up over breakfast before work. Those quiet mornings, sipping coffee and savoring something sweet, became one of my favorite parts of the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the summer, all the biking around Rotterdam made these small pleasures feel earned. My friends and I would detour to little cafés for coffee and pastries. And somewhere along the way, I also fell in love with solitary mornings: waking up early, stepping out while the city is still quiet, grabbing a fresh cup of coffee, and walking along the Maas. Sitting by the bridge or wandering along the water with that warm drink, I realized that these small, intentional moments with a coffee in hand and the city still asleep can feel profoundly joyful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for favorites: &lt;a href="https://share.google/B7L7gDV07JCklXWqc"&gt;Ripsnorter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://share.google/qPCPLUQTjMoKir2NJ"&gt;Cafecito&lt;/a&gt; for coffee; &lt;a href="https://share.google/DvSeEKO3eOeNw8VBs"&gt;Le Petit Jean&lt;/a&gt;, my regular breakfast spot with a friend; &lt;a href="https://share.google/lElWxLrXbHtdrmBql"&gt;Lila Bakery&lt;/a&gt; for its Eastern European cakes. My only frustration used to be that most bakeries in Rotterdam don’t open before 8 a.m. By then I’d already been up, ready for my treat with my nose pressed up against the windows waiting for the shutters to open. But discovering that the Albert Heijn next to my house has fresh pastéis de nata at 7 a.m., paired with a strong cup of coffee, felt like a small victory. A reminder that joy can be found in tiny, everyday discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the year, my love for pastries and coffee followed me on trips abroad. In July, a short vacation in Copenhagen was spent with quiet mornings wandering the city with Danish pastries and café lattés, and in late September, a trip to Nice and Paris with a coworker continued the streak with croissants, éclairs, and warm cafés. Those mornings in Copenhagen, Nice, and Paris reinforced a lesson I had been learning all year: delight isn’t reserved for big moments or grand adventures. It can be found in small, intentional acts, pausing to savor a pastry, sipping coffee slowly while the city wakes, or noticing the little rituals that make ordinary days richer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What began as a joke in Portugal has become a rhythm that follows me everywhere: runs that end with pastries, breakfasts with friends, bike rides that detour for coffee, and quiet walks with a warm cup in hand. Whether I’m in Rotterdam, Paris, or elsewhere, I’ve realized that joy often hides in the little things, the first sip of morning coffee, the flaky edge of a croissant, the stillness of a city before it wakes up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that fall is here, I’m excited to keep the ritual alive: to wake up early, explore quiet streets, and let soft, dark mornings remind me that life’s sweetness often comes in small, intentional moments. Coffee and pastries, in their simplicity, have shown me that joy doesn’t always arrive in grand gestures; it often lives quietly, in cups, crumbs, and the deliberate act of slowing down.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Note to Myself: Practice Gratitude More Often</title><link>/blog/a-note-to-myself-practice-gratitude-more-often/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/a-note-to-myself-practice-gratitude-more-often/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I catch myself living on autopilot. Days blur together with work, routines, endless scrolling and even if I get a lot done, it still doesn’t feel satisfying. There’s this undercurrent of “I’m not doing enough,” like no matter how much I check off, I’m behind somehow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when I stop and practice gratitude, that feeling shifts. Gratitude pulls me out of the “not enough” loop and reminds me of what’s already good. A good conversation. A quiet moment. The simple fact that I have people in my life I can lean on. When I notice those things, life feels fuller, lighter, and less about what’s missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also changes my mood in ways I don’t always expect. Gratitude makes me less restless, less caught up in comparing myself to others, and honestly more patient. It slows me down and lets me actually enjoy being here instead of racing toward some future moment that’s supposed to be better. Gratitude doesn’t erase problems, but it makes them feel smaller in the bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something I’ve been thinking about lately is practicing gratitude more outwardly. It’s easy to feel thankful in my head but never say it. I want to get better at actually expressing it with writing thank you notes, sending quick messages to friends or family, or even just saying it in the moment instead of letting the chance slip by. Because gratitude isn’t only about what I feel, it’s also about what I give. And I know from experience how much a simple “I appreciate you” can shift someone’s whole day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more I think about it, the more I realize gratitude isn’t just about happiness—it’s about connection. When I express it, I feel closer to people. I stop taking their presence for granted. I start to notice the ways they support me, show up for me, or simply make life better by being who they are. Gratitude makes relationships feel richer, not because anything changes on the outside, but because I see them more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So maybe this is really just a reminder to myself: gratitude isn’t something to save for special occasions or dramatic moments. It’s something to practice every day inwardly, so I can enjoy my own life more, and outwardly, so the people around me know they matter. Life feels more meaningful when I do, and maybe, if I’m consistent about it, gratitude can ripple out farther than I realize.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Beyond Brutal Honesty: Choosing Truth with Care</title><link>/blog/beyond-brutal-honesty-choosing-truth-with-care/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/beyond-brutal-honesty-choosing-truth-with-care/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;During my undergraduate years, I convinced myself that brutal honesty was the best way to live. I thought saying exactly what I believed, without filtering or softening, made me authentic and courageous. To me, sugarcoating felt dishonest, and I wanted to be someone who always “told it like it is.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, at 26, I find myself reflecting differently. The word brutal stands out to me more than it used to. Brutality implies force, harshness, and even a disregard for the other person. And when I look back, I realize that wasn’t really what I wanted to practice. What I valued was the truth, but truth doesn’t have to be brutal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still believe honesty is deeply important. It’s the foundation of trust, self-respect, and real connection. Without honesty, relationships become shallow, and growth becomes difficult. But I’ve learned that honesty, when shared without care, can land in ways that shut people down rather than open them up. Truth alone isn’t enough; how we share it matters just as much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over time, I’ve shifted toward what I now think of as &amp;ldquo;compassionate honesty&amp;rdquo;, speaking the truth with clarity, but also with empathy, so it can be received and reflected on. That doesn’t mean avoiding hard conversations. It means approaching them with compassion, remembering that honesty isn’t only about expressing myself, but also about creating space where growth and understanding are possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back, that phase of brutal honesty taught me to value truth and to have the courage to speak it. But today, I believe honesty becomes most powerful when paired with kindness. The world doesn’t need more &amp;ldquo;brutal&amp;rdquo; truths. It needs honesty that builds trust, nurtures connection, and helps us grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next time, keep honesty kind!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Quiet Shift: Three Months of Showing Up</title><link>/blog/the-quiet-shift-three-months-of-showing-up/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/the-quiet-shift-three-months-of-showing-up/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the biggest changes come not from grand gestures, but from the quiet routines we build and the small decisions we make every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time, I told myself I wanted to get in shape. It was one of those things that lived in the background, always there, always “something I should start doing.” I’d get a little momentum, then drop it. The intention was always there, the follow-through wasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to stay up way too late, usually around 1 or 2 a.m., and wake up at 8:30 or 9 still feeling tired and scattered. I didn’t feel terrible, but I didn’t feel great either. Just a constant sense that I wasn’t really operating at my best - not mentally, not physically, not in how I structured my time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things started to shift in March. I was on a trip to Portugal and spent some time hiking in Madeira. It was a beautiful place, and I really enjoyed the hikes — but I could also feel how out of shape I was. I managed fine, but part of me knew I should be feeling stronger than I did. That trip stuck with me, and when I got home, I decided I wanted to change a few things, not because I hit rock bottom or anything dramatic, but because I finally felt ready to prove to myself that I could stick with something and see it through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started going to gym regularly to begin with. Then I signed up for a trial session with a personal trainer mainly because it was free, and honestly, I didn’t expect much. But once I got there, things felt different. About halfway through, I half joked and half seriously said, “I think I might cry if you increase the weight again.” Without missing a beat, she replied, “You can cry, sure, but you are still doing it.” That moment made me realize we would probably work well together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do push myself sometimes, but I also tend to slip into my comfort zone more often than I’d like. Having someone who encourages me and keeps things challenging—but not overwhelming—has made a big difference. She pushes me, checks in regularly, and keeps me moving forward. This balance of structure and support has really helped me stay focused and committed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, I’ve built a routine that actually works. I wake up at 6 a.m. now, which felt impossible not that long ago. I go to the gym five times a week, mainly strength training. I’ve lost around 6kg and feel noticeably stronger. I’ve also gotten back into biking consistently, something I’ve always loved! Being in the Netherlands makes it easy to ride everywhere, and on weekends I’ll go out for long rides. Sometimes solo, sometimes with friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biking has become more social, which I really enjoy. I even convinced one of my friends to get into it. Riding together has become a fun way to hang out. It’s not just about the workout or clearing my head anymore, it’s also about spending time with people I enjoy. That said, I still love my solo rides. There’s something about being on the road alone, with space to think (or not think at all), that really helps me reset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the recent highlights was a 152km ride. It was my longest in a while, and I finished feeling strong. If I had fueled better, I’m pretty sure I could’ve gone another 50. That kind of ride is a reminder that progress isn’t just a feeling, it’s something you can see and measure. I’ve got a couple longer rides I want to do soon — Rotterdam to Ghent (~160km) and Rotterdam to Groningen (~265km). They’re not about proving anything to anyone else. They’re just quiet benchmarks to see how far I’ve come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These past few months, I’ve also started ending my days with nighttime walks. They’ve become one of my favorite parts of the day — a time to reflect, unwind, and take stock of where I’m at. Sometimes I go alone, other times I’ll have a friend join me and we’ll just talk about whatever’s on our minds. It’s simple, but it’s helped me stay more in tune with myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s still more I want to do. I’d like to get more comfortable with running again, keep building strength, maybe add new challenges along the way. But I’m not rushing anything. I’m enjoying how this all fits into my life now, without forcing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shift didn’t come from turning 26 — that was just a marker I used to get started. What’s kept me going is seeing progress, feeling better in my own body, and actually enjoying the process. I’m not chasing some perfect version of myself. I’m just getting closer to the person I’ve always wanted to be. And for now, that feels like more than enough!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Be selfish to be selfless</title><link>/blog/be-selfish-to-be-selfless/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/be-selfish-to-be-selfless/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Be selfish to be selfless. Aren’t both the words the antonyms of each other? What is this guy on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though the statement looks contradictory, looking at it on a deeper level reveals the exquisite intuitiveness it possesses. That is the purpose of this post, to look at the statement on a deeper level and express my views on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although one might suggest that being a selfless person is the ultimate goal, I would argue that one cannot be a selfless person without being selfish first. In short I would say it means that the more you know yourself, the more you can give.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every individual is unique, no other person in the world will share the exact same interests or do things the exact same way. In your journey of understanding yourself, it is required of you to be true to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are true to yourself, you are being true to the rest of the world. Being true to yourself is the best thing a person can do as you are representing yourself to others as the true individual you are. People get to like you or dislike you for your true self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being selfish here means that you remain true to yourself and do the things that help you learn about yourself. Once you understand yourself, you start understanding what you have that you can provide and allow you to be truly selfless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mark of the immature man is that he wants to die nobly for a cause, while the mark of the mature man is that he wants to live humbly for one.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;em&gt;- Wilhelm Stekel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also believe that being truly selfless requires a person to find their own happiness first before helping others find their happiness. Unless you are truly happy, you will give only with an expectation of something in return that makes you happy and this makes your selfless act into a selfish act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore one must look to fill their life with happiness first before they can help fill happiness in other people’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be truly selfless, one must be able to give without any expectations. It is the expectations that kill true selflessness. Being selfish is the path to true selflessness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next time, be a little selfish to be a lot more selfless.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why strong opinions matter</title><link>/blog/why-strong-opinions-matter/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/why-strong-opinions-matter/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Over the course of my journey of self improvement, I have realized that my ultimate goal in life is to be the best version of myself that I can be. The process that I must adopt to achieve the goal is to be a little less wrong tomorrow than I am today. To do that, I need to assess who I am today, and who I want to be tomorrow. To know the latter, I need to have strong opinions on what is right and what is not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing good ever came from meekly following the general consensus unquestioningly. All the advancements we have today were all born from a single question - &amp;ldquo;Why?&amp;rdquo; Aristarchus believed that the Sun was at the centre of the universe. He believed that at a time when everyone was certain that everything revolved around Earth. Today, we know better than Aristarchus, but only because people dared to challenge him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having strong opinions provides people a helping hand in their quest for truth. However, it must be mentioned that having strong opinions without being open to criticism and introspection causes more harm than good. Keeping an open mind and being ready to change your opinions when they have been proven to be wrong is healthier than being steadfast in your beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To establish a strong opinion, one must be brutally honest to themselves. Arriving at a strong opinion requires the individual to be able to make a series of logical arguments to justify their conclusion. The process of constructing logical arguments will allow the person to test their own opinion for any gaps in the reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are not entitled to your opinion. You are entitled to your informed opinion. No one is entitled to be ignorant.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;em&gt;- Harlan Ellison&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having strong opinions is good, but having one just for the sake of one is not good. One cannot form an opinion on a subject they know nothing about. The prerequisite to forming an opinion is research. Whether it is politics or religion or anything else thought up by man, to form an opinion, let alone a strong one, an understanding of the topic is mandatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One must also realize that neither do most people need to agree with your opinions, nor do you need to change your opinions to satisfy most of the people. To appear acceptable to most people, one must present their views in a moderate way. But this approach puts you on a path further away from the truth. If you are looking for your truth, you must be willing to articulate your extreme ideas to others because they may not share your views and can offer you perspectives that you may have missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When your opinion is proven wrong, it may make you feel ignorant, but that could be your signal to stop and learn a bit more with an open mind. You must remember it is the cost you must pay in pursuit of the truth. The goal, after all, is to be less wrong tomorrow than you are today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next time! Hoping to meet you as a better person than I am today!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>