<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Karthik Ganeshram</title><link>/categories/personal/</link><description>Recent content from Karthik Ganeshram</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>One Year In: A Whirlwind of Small Wonders</title><link>/blog/one-year-in-a-whirlwind-of-small-wonders/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/one-year-in-a-whirlwind-of-small-wonders/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I moved to Europe on my birthday last year with suitcases packed, heart full, old housemates seeing me off. It was one of those life shifts that felt equal parts exhilarating and heavy. An ending, a beginning, and the quiet whisper that kept repeating in my head: If not now, when?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rotterdam has been home for a year now, and though the streets once felt foreign, I’m slowly building a rhythm. Living alone for the first time wasn’t easy. After years of roommates and shared spaces, the quiet was loud. But over time, I began filling that space - with music, books, plants, and spontaneous social adventures that taught me more about myself than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living alone also meant I had to actively seek connection. I joined meetups, used apps like Timeleft to have dinners with strangers, and nudged myself into unfamiliar social settings. One of the wildest nights started with me saying a quick hello to a friend at an African music festival, despite having just cycled 114 km earlier that day and turned into bar hopping, only to end up spontaneously celebrating a complete stranger’s birthday right after we met. Moments like those made me realize how quickly life was beginning to root itself, even in a new place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few familiar faces from undergrad also live here, and reconnecting with them added another layer of comfort. One friend, whose family still lives in the same apartment complex as mine back home, has known me for over 21 years. Sharing the same streets again, this time in a different country brought a strange kind of full circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My social circle here is wildly eclectic. We’ve had board game marathons, dinners that stretch until dawn, and a very committed Mexican food crawl where we jumped from one taqueria to the next, rating tacos like connoisseurs. It’s random, it’s chaotic, and it’s perfect in its own way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cycling has become a cornerstone of my life here. I finally got myself a proper gravel bike and started exploring the Netherlands with it. These long rides has become a my form of meditation to recharge, escape, and feel connected to this new home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/biking_journey.jpg" alt="Bike on top of a bridge"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professionally, this has been a year of growth. I’ve taken on more responsibility, found genuine enjoyment in my work, and gave a talk at Wasm I/O in Barcelona. I flew in early to hang out with a coworker I’d known for a while, and that extra time gave us a chance to connect outside of meetings and work chat. I also now live closer to my manager in Ghent (my favorite city in Belgium), and our co-working sessions there have doubled as excuses to enjoy a city I can’t seem to get enough of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/wasmio_2025_talk.jpg" alt="Speaking at wasmio"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the highlights was a spontaneous trip to Portugal, specifically Madeira. The trip was with someone I had only met four months earlier, but we clicked quickly and easily. I tagged along on his vacation because I didn’t have plans of my own, and it turned into one of the most fulfilling experiences I’ve had. It reminded me how beautiful and rewarding life can be when you leave space for the unexpected. It was also my first true vacation since starting full-time work after grad school and now I want more of that blend of travel, presence, and freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/madeira.jpg" alt="madeira trail"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of 2024, I was feeling the weight of uncertainty trying to have everything figured out. But as 2025 began, something shifted. I started embracing the mess, the unknown, the in-between. I’ve been leaning into the idea of don’t prepone your suffering as a reminder not to overthink what hasn’t happened yet, to give the present the attention it deserves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That mindset has created space for other joys. I’ve lost 8 kilos, started going to the gym, and while my flat feet interrupted my attempt at running, I’m hoping to pick it back up someday. I’ve started baking more, and I’m on track to read 30 books this year. The Book of Why and Clear Thinking have stuck with me most. I’ve also learned a lot about financial literacy, something I never prioritized before, but now find deeply grounding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My apartment is now home to 42 plants (and counting). My dad helped me tend to them during his visits, while my mom took over the kitchen and cooked for me like I was 12 again. We took a mini tour through Germany and Belgium together, exploring cities and small towns I likely wouldn’t have found alone. Those moments felt like gifts, gently stitched into this bigger, unfamiliar year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/home_jungle.jpg" alt="a bunch of new plants"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also got to visit Christmas markets with my friends. Warm drinks in our hands and freezing air, It felt like walking through a living postcard, one I didn’t know I needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I want more. More travel laptop in hand, new cities as my backdrop. More presence. More exploration maybe pottery, definitely terrariums. More openness. Build deeper bonds. More of the good kind of uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A year ago, I didn’t have a roadmap. I just followed a feeling. Now, on the other side of 12 months filled with randomness, beauty, discomfort, and growth. I see how deeply worthwhile it’s all been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, I still don’t have it all figured out but that the best part!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title> My Biking journey - Davis to San Francisco</title><link>/blog/my-biking-journey-davis-to-san-francisco/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/my-biking-journey-davis-to-san-francisco/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I was never the one to be excited about biking. Biking was just a tool to get from place to place for me. Never in my wildest dreams did I ever expect it to become my favorite hobby. It all changed as I returned to Davis to pursue my master&amp;rsquo;s degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I vividly remember the first time I rode to the campus and back. I was so exhausted by it. It was not even a long ride, it was only 10km (6 miles) in total. Going from that to being able to ride from Davis to San Francisco (150km or 93 miles) has been an interesting journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-beginning"&gt;The Beginning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I arrived in the USA, I was intrigued when I saw Mike (my host) working on bikes. We started having conversations about different things related to biking. Then he along with Cee (my other host) decided to gift me a road bike that fit me. It is one of the best presents I have ever received. I have never had a bike that fit me properly and never a road bike. That is where my biking as a hobby began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started riding around Davis with Mike. Being in Davis, a bike-friendly town helped enhance my experience. Somewhere along the way, biking had gone from just being a means of getting where I needed to be to something that I actually enjoyed doing. I started riding more often and seeing my interest in biking, Mike helped me upgrade the bike and introduced me to biking gear that helped improve my experience much more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-plan"&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I started biking to places outside Davis towards the end of 2021. As 2022 was approaching, I made it my goal to bike from Davis to San Francisco during the summer of 2022. I wanted to start training for it consistently. I started riding further each time and more regularly. As I rode, I got to go through some nice routes to places like Winters and Dixon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As spring break approached, I was feeling ambitious and decided to attempt going from Davis to San Francisco during the break. It was very ambitious for me as I had not even gone half the distance on a single ride before. I just decided to attempt it, thinking that the worst thing that could happen was me failing it. I decided to go for it as I saw it as a win-win situation, no matter what happened. If I didn&amp;rsquo;t make it, I would know how far I could go and how much I had to improve to accomplish the goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/Davis2SFroute.png" alt="Rotue from Davis to SF"&gt;&lt;em&gt;bike route from Davis to SF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-journey"&gt;The journey&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to attempt biking from Davis to San Francisco on March 21st, 2022. It was also helpful that my friends decided to drive down to San Francisco to pick me up and drive me back to Davis. I slept early the previous night so I could start early in the morning. I left the house at 4:50am and started pedaling towards the destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/Davis2SFride.jpg" alt="Biking early in the morning"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Biking early in the morning&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first 3 hours of the journey were very smooth, I had gone a little more than a third of the way passing Dixon, Vacaville, and reached Fairfield. The roads were pretty good although it was mostly farm roads. As I reached Fairfield, my rear tire had a puncture and I almost decided the ride was over. But as it was to be, the ride was not over. Mike drove up to me and helped me get back on the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I got past Fairfield, the terrain changed from being fairly smooth to being hilly. It was where the ride started being challenging. Hills and bridges have always been my least favorite place to ride. My motivation to make it to San Francisco made me climb the uphill slopes. My effort in climbing the uphill slopes was well worth it as the reward of being able to coast downhill was both exciting and terrifying. I got to descend at around 64kmph (40mph) at some places. The roads were not the greatest and therefore I had to start slowing down when riding downhill for my own safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As time went along, it was interesting for me to note that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t feeling tired cycling but the biggest problem was the fact that I had packed too much into my backpack. It was becoming rather uncomfortable as I had to bike leaning forward. It is a lesson that I have learned that will help me in the future. I had carried too much food thinking I would need it. Google maps didn&amp;rsquo;t help my cause much by leading me to a road that was closed and also leading to a trail via a dirt path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was slowly making it towards San Francisco when disaster struck again. I was in the final stretch and my rear tire blew up again. I was within touching distance, I was 12 miles (20km) from the Golden Gate bridge. Although I was pretty confident and energetic about making it, I had to end the ride due to the unfortunate circumstance. The ride came to an end after 8 hours of riding excluding breaks. I was then picked up by my friends. Then, I made it to San Francisco, although it was by car and not by bike as originally planned. I still see the trip as a win. The day ended with us grabbing dinner and spending some time in San Francisco before returning back to Davis to complete an eventful day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/Davis2SFfinal.jpg" alt="Ending the evening at SF"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ending the day at SF with my friends&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to give my special thanks to David and Crystal for deciding to drive down to San Francisco and then pick me up when I needed it. You guys are lifesavers. From having met not so long ago to driving to San Francisco to help me out, I am glad to have met you. I also want to give a big thanks to Mike and Cee from the bottom of my heart for helping me find my passion for biking and making it possible for me to pursue it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a fun experience and I learned a lot along the way. It was an entirely new experience and my horizons have expanded giving me the confidence to ride more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pedaling onto the next destination!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title> A peek into my life and a Brief Introduction</title><link>/blog/a-peek-into-my-life-and-a-brief-introduction/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/a-peek-into-my-life-and-a-brief-introduction/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I was born into a wonderful family in Chennai, a city in South India. And this blog is all about how I got to where I am today, where I am going from here and the journey in between. It will have tech, some thoughts about the last book I read, and a lot of musings about philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My fascination with computers and programming began, as might be the case for many of you, with “Hello World.” Typing out the program and seeing the words appear on the screen gave me a feeling of satisfaction that I can still remember. Begining there my life has taken me through a journey towards finding my interests in computer architecutre and parallel processing. Apart from it, I enjoy web development. With a healthy mix of hard work and luck, I was able to get into UC Davis and where I hope to do what I love the most - understanding computers in depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first memories of videogames are those of me playing Age of Empires on my PC after school while my cousin sat with me and cheered me on. I play the game even today. Well, that and any outdoor sport. I enjoy reading and discussing various viewpoints in life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you might be wondering why my blog is anything different from the hundreds of others. It isn’t! It is just a way for me document my journey towards a better personal and professional life. If my journey and experience helps you somehow, that is an added plus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next time, stay safe and healthy!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>